Jacobs family papers, 1861-1909 (bulk 1878-1890)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Jacobs family papers, 1861-1909 (bulk 1878-1890)
AZ 196
Jacobs Family
The collection consists of correspondence, letter books, invoices, financial statements, ledgers, journals, receipts, cancelled checks, debit and credit memos, certificate of deposit stubs, draft registers, collection registers, and remittance registers produced by the daily mercantile and banking business of Lionel and Barron Jacobs.
32 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Lionel (1840-1922) and Barron (1846-1936) Jacobs arrived in Tucson in 1867 to open a general store. Their father, Mark I. Jacobs (1816-1894), was an established merchant in San Francisco. The mercantile business operated as M.I. Jacobs and Company until 1875 when Mark Jacobs' active involvement ceased and it then became known as L.M. Jacobs and Company.
It was a family business serving the mining camps and military establishments in Arizona during the 1870s. Mark Jacobs' sons-in-law, Marcus Katz, Jacob Cohn, Martin Calisher, Wolff Cohn, and their sons were involved in the merchant and money exchange business. Abraham Franklin, the son of Maurice and Victoria Jacobs Franklin, established a branch store in Safford in 1878; and Maurice Calisher, son of Martin and Fanny Jacobs Calisher, operated a store in Florence.
Their money exchange business grew significantly by 1871; gold coin from San Francisco was exchanged for paper money in Tucson. In 1879, they established the Pima County Bank in Tucson with Barron Jacobs as cashier. A branch agency, Pima County Bank, was also established in Tombstone under the management of Lionel Jacobs. Phillip W. Smith, Heyman Solomon, and Allen Springer were cashiers at various times. The brothers gave up the mercantile part of the business in 1880 to concentrate on banking.
The banks went through several changes over the years. Pima County Bank became, successively, First National Bank of Tucson in 1882, Bank of Tucson in 1886, and Consolidated Bank of Tucson in 1887. Merrill P. Freeman was cashier for Consolidated Bank of Tucson. He resigned in 1887 and established the Santa Cruz Valley Bank. In 1890, the Jacobs brothers sold their ownership of Consolidated Bank of Tucson, purchased the Santa Cruz Valley Bank, and changed its name to the Arizona National Bank. The Agency Pima County Bank in Tombstone changed its name to Cochise County Bank in 1882, and finally closed early in 1890 because of Tombstone's depressed economy following the mine closures.
Lionel and Barron were active in Tucson social life and resided for a time at the Owl's Club, a bachelor's residence for prominent businessmen. They were active in forming the Tucson Literary Society in 1873. Lionel was appointed to the Pima County Board of Supervisors in 1871, was Treasurer of the Territorial Legislature in 1873, and also served on the Tucson City Council. He married Bertha Frank (1865-1955) of San Francisco. He died February 7, 1922 in San Francisco. Barron served as Treasurer of the Territorial Legislature for the two months prior to Lionel. He married Henrietta (Yetta) and they had one daughter, Hilda. Barron died on November 15, 1936 in Washington, D.C., where his daughter resided.
Organization
This collection is organized into two series:
I. Unbound Papers, 1861-1896
II. Bound Volumes, 1867-1909
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of correspondence, letter books, invoices, financial statements, ledgers, journals, receipts, cancelled checks, debit and credit memos, certificate of deposit stubs, draft registers, collection registers, and remittance registers produced by the daily mercantile and banking business of Lionel and Barron Jacobs.
Correspondence includes letters between Mark Jacobs and his sons, Lionel and Barron, concerning business conditions, needs and decisions. Until 1872, Mark managed the firm through his regular letters to his sons in Tucson. From 1872 to 1875, Lionel is residing mostly in San Francisco and directing the business for his father. For this period, the business correspondence is mainly between Lionel in San Francisco and Barron in Tucson. Barron's replies are found in the bound letter books. There is also correspondence from family and friends to Lionel and Barron, 1871 to 1876, including a few letters from their nephew, Selim M. Franklin, who later became a prominent Tucson citizen.
The rest of the correspondence relates to business matters although some correspondents such as Abraham Franklin, J.B. Collins, and Joe Goldwater include information on local conditions in their letters. From 1878 to 1880, Abraham Franklin writes detailed letters while establishing a branch store in Safford, Arizona. J.B. Collins writes of an 1880 incident when Isaac Clanton, Joe Hill, and Johnny Ringo went on a shooting spree at Jacob's mill and Abraham Franklin's store in Safford. Joe Goldwater owns stores in Bisbee, Contention, and Fairbanks, Arizona, and comments on daily events.
Materials documenting the purchase of goods from New York, San Francisco, and Mexico and the shipment of goods to Tucson and other locations in southern Arizona, 1861 to 1879, include invoices, correspondence, receipts, and financial statements. The Jacobs brothers contracted with private freighters such as Joseph Pierson, Juan Fernandez, Pedro Aguirre, and the Hooper and Whiting Company to transport their goods. David Neahr was their primary forwarding agent; he transferred goods from steamers at Yuma to freight wagons bound for Tucson. The Jacobs Company also served as forwarding agent for the Terrenate Flour Mill in Jerante, Sonora. Owner Joseph Pierson sent flour to L.M. Jacobs and Company which sold it mainly to nearby military forts.
Goods were purchased in New York and San Francisco and shipped by steamer up the Colorado River to Yuma, then by freight wagons easterly across the desert to Tucson. Goods were also purchased in Mexico and shipped north to Tucson from Guaymas, Mexico. The goods sold were then delivered to locations throughout Southern Arizona including Oatman, Mission Camp, Gila Bend, Desert Station, Sacaton, Altar, Picacho, Apache Camp, Tombstone, Safford, Florence, Camp Grant, Camp Thomas, Fort Yuma and others.
Mercantile records representing the sale of goods to individuals, companies, and the military include journals, ledgers, invoices, daily sales blotters, inventories, and registers of distilled spirits received and sold, 1867 to 1880. The content of these records is described in the Inventory and Series Description section of this finding aid. Many of these records provide an itemized record of items purchased and prices paid. Their customers include early residents of Tucson, Tombstone, and southern Arizona. Selected names are noted in the inventory but many others exist in the records.
Banking records consist of journals, ledgers, daily exchange records, certificate of deposit stubs, money order stubs, checks, debit and credit memos, notes and bills receivable, collection registers, remittance registers, draft registers, records of payments for government and other agencies and trial balance sheets. Explanations of information provided in the records is included in the Inventory and Series Description section of this finding aid. The majority of records relate to the Cochise County Bank, but Pima County Bank and Arizona National Bank are also well represented. While most of the loose papers of banking correspondence and cancelled checks relate to the Cochise County Bank, the bound volumes are more evenly divided between banks.
This collection provides detailed evidence of mercantile and banking practices at the end of the 19th century. Additional highlights include 1875 bankruptcy papers for the mercantile company of Philip Drachman and Isaac Goldberg; agreements to supply goods to military camps; daily sales blotters from as early as 1867 showing customer name, items purchased and price paid for each item; an 1870 Citizens Subscription of Indian Campaign giving names and amount contributed; receipt books that show customer name, items shipped, and where shipped, including many for Camp Grant; Distilled Spirits Received and Sold records which give customer name, place, and number of gallons of whiskey delivered; lists of bank depositors showing names of Tombstone and Tucson citizens with amounts they have on deposit; and other bank transactions for individuals showing what they deposited, borrowed, and paid out.
Some materials in this collection are in Spanish.
Related Material
Materials concerning the Jacobs family are also located at the Arizona Historical Society, Tucson in collection number MS 380.
Bibliography
Moore, Dawn. "Pioneer Banking in Tucson: Lionel and Barron Jacobs and the Founding of the Pima County Bank," Arizona and the West, 24(4), Winter 1982, p. 305-318.
Schweikart, Larry. "You Can Count On It: The birth of banking in Arizona," Journal of Arizona History, 22(3), Autumn 1981, pp. 349-368.
Access Terms
Jacobs, Lionel, 1841-1922 -- Archives
Jacobs, Barron M., 1847-1936 -- Archives
Jacobs, Mark I. -- Archives
L.M. Jacobs and Company -- Records and correspondence
Cochise County Bank (Ariz.) -- Records and correspondence
Arizona National Bank -- Records and correspondence
Pima County Bank -- Records and correspondence
Merchants -- Arizona -- History -- Sources
Bankers -- Arizona -- History -- Sources
Jews -- Arizona -- History -- Sources
Frontier and pioneer life -- Arizona -- History -- Sources
Banks and banking -- Arizona -- History -- Sources
Retail trade -- Arizona -- History -- Sources
Freight and freightage -- West (U.S.)
Military bases -- Arizona -- History -- Sources
Pioneers -- Arizona
Tucson (Ariz.) -- History -- Sources
West (U.S.) -- Economic conditions -- 19th century
Tombstone (Ariz.) -- History -- To 1912 -- Sources
Ledgers
Correspondence
Account Books
Container List
- Series I: Unbound Papers, 1861-1896
  Series I consists of three subseries: General Unbound Papers, 1861-1878; Unbound Records of the Agency Pima County Bank of Tombstone, Cochise County Bank, and Santa Cruz Valley Bank, 1879-1891; and Unbound Records of Arizona National Bank, 1889-1896. Within the subseries are correspondence, invoices, financial statements, accounts, cancelled checks, debit and credit memos, certificate of deposit stubs, and other materials which are arranged chronologically within record type in each subseries. General papers include personal and family correspondence and records relating to L.M. Jacobs and Company. Agency Pima County Bank and Arizona National Bank records document bank transactions.
  - General Unbound Papers, 1861-1878
    - Correspondence re: shipping, freighting, and merchandise between San Diego, San Francisco and Tucson. Chief correspondent is David Neahr of Yuma. 1861-1875 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Cash reports, invoices, income statements, and account summaries for store business. 1871-1872 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Receipts, invoices, account statements; includes agreement to furnish beef to U.S. military camps. 1873-1874 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Receipts, invoices, orders. January-August, 1875 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Receipts, invoices; includes bankruptcy papers for company of Philip Drachman and Isaac Goldberg. September-December, 1875 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence from M.I. Jacobs in San Francisco to his sons, Lionel and Barron in Tucson; includes business matters and personal philosophy. 1868-1871 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence from M.I. Jacobs to Barron and Lionel, 1872, and from Lionel in San Francisco to Barron in Tucson, 1873-1875, chiefly concerning store business. 1872-May, 1875 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence from Lionel in San Francisco to Barron in Tucson concerning merchandise selection and suppliers. June-November, 1875 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence to Lionel from family members; includes letters from Lionel in New York and Paris to Barron in Tucson and letters from Selim M. Franklin, nephew, from Berkeley. 1871-1876 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence to Lionel from family and friends. 1871-1875 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, business and invoices for purchases in New York. Correspondents include David Neahr. January-February, 1876 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, business, customer orders, suppliers invoices. March, 1876-December, 1877 (Box 2, Folder 4-8)
    - Correspondence from M.I. Jacobs to Barron and Lionel concerning money matters. 1876-1877 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Banking and customer orders; Pima County Bank and Arizona National Bank of Tucson, Arizona. No Date (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Business correspondence, New York purchase invoices, financial accounts; includes petty ledger balances listing many Tucsonans names and dollar amounts. Also includes letters from Abraham Franklin while establishing new store in Safford, Arizona. January-October, 1878 (Box 3, Folder 3-7)
    - Financial accounts, loan accounts, San Francisco purchase invoices, and orders; includes supply order from Isaac Clanton. November-December, 1878 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Cancelled checks. July-August, 1878 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Accounts, invoices, purchase invoices; includes correspondence from Abraham Franklin at store in Safford, Arizona. January-June, 1879 (Box 4, Folder 3-6)
    - Accounts, invoices, purchase invoices, and Pima County Bank weekly statements. July-September, 1879 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Unbound Records: Agency Pima County Bank of Tombstone, Cochise County Bank, First National Bank of Tucson, and Santa Cruz Valley Bank, 1877-1891
    - Agency Pima County Bank of Tombstone: Correspondence, business, invoices, weekly statements. October-December, 1879 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
    - Agency Pima County Bank of Tombstone: Correspondence from M.I. Jacobs in San Francisco to Barron in Tucson, chiefly business. June-November, 1879 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Agency Pima County Bank of Tombstone: Correspondence from Lionel in San Francisco to Barron, chiefly business. August-November, 1879 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Agency Pima County Bank of Tombstone: Cancelled checks, check register, deposit slips. 1879 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Agency Pima County Bank of Tombstone: Correspondence, business, invoices; includes letter to Barron from J.B. Collins at Maxey, Ariz. near Fort Thomas. He details a shooting spree by Isaac Clanton and others at the Jacobs' mill in Safford. January-July, 1880 (Box 5, Folder 6-7)
    - Agency Pima County Bank of Tombstone: Lists of checks drawn on Tombstone branch, orders to pay. August, 1880 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Agency Pima County Bank of Tombstone: Lists of checks drawn on Tombstone branch. September-December, 1880 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Agency Pima County Bank of Tombstone: Correspondence from M.I. Jacobs to Barron and Lionel; chiefly business. July-November, 1880 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Agency Pima County Bank of Tombstone: Cancelled checks, deposit slips. 1880 (Box 6, Folder 3-4)
    - Agency Pima County Bank of Tombstone: Correspondence concerning banking, monthly lists of balances consisting of Tombstone residents names and amounts including V.W. Earp, J.H. Behan, J.H. Slaughter and others. January-August, 1881 (Box 6, Folder 5-8)
    - Agency Pima County Bank of Tombstone: Banking transactions and correspondence. September-December, 1881 (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
    - Agency Pima County Bank of Tombstone: Cancelled checks, deposit slips. 1881 (Box 7, Folder 3-4)
    - Agency Pima County Bank of Tombstone: Banking transactions, lists of checks drawn on bank. (name changes to Cochise County Bank). January-May, 1882 (Box 7, Folder 5-7)
    - Cochise County Bank: Banking correspondence and lists of checks drawn. June-December, 1882 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Cochise County Bank: Cancelled checks, debit/credit memos, deposit slips. 1882 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Cochise County Bank: Certificates of deposit. 1882 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Cochise County Bank: Banking correspondence and transactions. January-April, 1883 (Box 8, Folder 5-6)
    - Cochise County Bank: Banking correspondence and transactions. May-December, 1883 (Box 9, Folder 1-3)
    - Cochise County Bank: Cancelled checks, deposit slips. 1883 (Box 9, Folder 4-5)
    - Cochise County Bank: Certificates of deposit. 1883 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Cochise County Bank: Various transactions. January-December, 1884 (Box 10, Folder 1-3)
    - Cochise County Bank: transactions with A.A. Castenada and Company. Correspondence from Joe Goldwater of this company; contains brief mentions of Bisbee occurrences. March-September, 1884 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Cochise County Bank: Transactions with Chemical National Bank, N.Y. including monthly statements. 1884 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Cochise County Bank: Transactions with First National Bank of Tucson including monthly statements of account. 1884 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Cochise County Bank: Transactions with First National Bank of San Francisco. 1884 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - First National Bank of Tucson: Transactions with National Park Bank, N.Y. 1884 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Cochise County Bank: Deposit slips, credit memos. 1884 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Cochise County Bank: Cancelled checks, debit memos. 1884 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Cochise County Bank: Transactions, statements of accounts with other banks. January-May, 1885 (Box 11, Folder 3-6)
    - Cochise County Bank: Transactions; folder 7 includes lists of payees of Cochise County warrants. June-December, 1885 (Box 12, Folder 1-7)
    - Cochise County Bank: Cancelled checks, debit memos, deposit slips. 1885 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Cochise County Bank: Transactions; Bank of California, San Francisco account transactions with Cochise County Bank. 1885 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Cochise County Bank: Transactions; The Bank of Tucson account transactions with Cochise County Bank. February-December, 1885 (Box 13, Folder 2-3)
    - Cochise County Bank: Transactions with A.A. Castenada and Company; includes correspondence from Joe Goldwater. 1885 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Cochise County Bank: Transactions with Chemical National Bank. 1885 (Box 13, Folder 5-6)
    - Cochise County Bank: Correspondence and transactions from Copper Queen Mining Company; Ben Williams, Superintendent. 1885 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Cochise County Bank: Correspondence and transactions with J. Goldwater and Company; includes comments on Bisbee. February-June, 1885 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Cochise County Bank: Correspondence and transactions with J. Goldwater and Company; includes comments on Bisbee. July-December, 1885 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Cochise County Bank: Correspondence concerning transactions with Zeckendorf and Company, Tucson. 1885 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Cochise County Bank: Correspondence and transactions with various banks and customers. January-October, 1886 (Box 14, Folder 3-6)
    - Cochise County Bank: Correspondence and transactions with various banks and customers. November-December, 1886 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Cochise County Bank: Transactions with Bank of Tucson. 1886 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Cochise County Bank: Transactions with Bank of California, San Francisco. 1886 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Cochise County Bank: Transactions with Copper Queen Mining Company. 1886 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Cochise County Bank: Transactions with Chemical National Bank. 1886 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Cochise County Bank: Transactions with First National Bank, Deming, N.M. 1886 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Cochise County Bank: Transactions with J. Goldwater and Company, Bisbee, Fairbanks, and Contention. 1886 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Cochise County Bank: Transactions with Zeckendorf and Company. 1886 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Cochise County Bank: Cancelled checks, debit memos. 1886 (Box 16, Folder 1-2)
    - Cochise County Bank: Correspondence and transactions; includes Chemical National Bank, Consolidated Bank of Tucson. 1887 (Box 16, Folder 3-7)
    - Cochise County Bank: Cancelled checks, debit memos. 1887 (Box 17, Folder 1-2)
    - Cochise County Bank: Correspondence and transactions. 1887 (Box 17, Folder 3-8)
    - Cochise County Bank: Transactions with Bank of California, San Francisco. 1888 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Cochise County Bank: Transactions with Consolidated Bank of Tucson. 1888 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Cochise County Bank: Transactions with J. Goldwater and Company. 1888 (Box 18, Folder 3-5)
    - Cochise County Bank: Cancelled checks, debit memos. 1888 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Santa Cruz Valley Bank: Miscellaneous transactions customers include Colin Cameron, J.H. Slaughter, and J. Goldwater and Company. 1889 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Santa Cruz Valley Bank: Cancelled checks, debit memos, credit memos. 1889 (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Santa Cruz Valley Bank: Transactions; includes Colin Cameron and San Rafael Cattle Company banking. January-February, 1889 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Santa Cruz Valley Bank: Transactions. March-December, 1890 (Box 19, Folder 2-4)
    - Santa Cruz Valley Bank: Transactions with Chemical National Bank. 1890 (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Santa Cruz Valley Bank: Transactions with London, Paris and American Bank. 1890 (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - Santa Cruz Valley Bank: State National Bank, El Paso. 1890 (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - Santa Cruz Valley Bank: Checks. 1890 (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - Santa Cruz Valley Bank: Transactions, general. 1891 (Box 19, Folder 9)
    - Arizona National Bank (known earlier as the Santa Cruz Valley Bank): Transactions, general. 1891 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Arizona National Bank: Transactions with Chemical National Bank. 1891 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Arizona National Bank: Transactions with London, Paris and American Bank. 1891 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Arizona National Bank: Transactions with State National Bank, El Paso. 1891 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Arizona National Bank: Transactions, general. 1892 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Arizona National Bank: Transactions with Bank of Tombstone. 1892 (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - Arizona National Bank: Transactions with London, Paris and American Bank. 1892 (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - Arizona National Bank: Transactions with State National Bank, El Paso. 1892 (Box 21, Folder 1-2)
    - Arizona National Bank: Transactions with Valley Bank of Phoenix. 1892 (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Arizona National Bank: Transactions, general; chiefly National Bank of Commerce, Saint Louis and First National Bank of Chicago. 1893 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - Arizona National Bank: Transactions with Bank of Tombstone. 1893 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Arizona National Bank: Transactions with State National Bank, El Paso. 1893 (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Arizona National Bank: Transactions with Valley Bank of Phoenix. 1893 (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - Arizona National Bank: Transactions, general. January-July, 1894 (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - Arizona National Bank: Transactions, general. August-December, 1894 (Box 22, Folder 1-2)
    - Arizona National Bank: Transactions, general. 1895 (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - Arizona National Bank: Transactions with Chemical National Bank. 1895 (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - Arizona National Bank: Transactions with Farmers and Merchants Bank, Los Angeles. 1895 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - Arizona National Bank: Transactions with Phoenix National Bank. 1895 (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - Arizona National Bank: Transactions with State National Bank, El Paso. 1895 (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - Arizona National Bank: Transactions with London, Paris and American Bank. 1895 (Box 23, Folder 1-4)
    - Arizona National Bank: Cancelled checks from The Exchange Bank, N.M. and Old Abe Company in White Oaks, N.M. No apparent connection to the Arizona banks. 1898-1900 (Box 23, Folder 5)